I'm going to talk about a failure of intuition
سأقوم بالتحدث عن فشل الحدس
that many of us suffer from.
الذي يعاني معظمنا منه.
It's really a failure to detect a certain kind of danger.
هو في الواقع الفشل في تحرِّي نوع محدد من الخطر.
I'm going to describe a scenario
سوف أقوم بوصف سيناريو
that I think is both terrifying
أظنه مخيفاً
and likely to occur,
ومن المرجح أن يحدث،
and that's not a good combination,
وهذا ليس مزيجاً جيداً،
as it turns out.
كما سيبدو.
And yet rather than be scared, most of you will feel
ومع ذلك، بدلاً من الخوف، سيشعر معظمكم
that what I'm talking about is kind of cool.
بأن ما أتحدُّث عنه مثير نوعاً ما.
I'm going to describe how the gains we make
سأقوم بوصف كيف أن المكاسب التي نحصل عليها
in artificial intelligence
من الذكاء الاصطناعي
could ultimately destroy us.
يمكن في النهاية أن تدمرنا.
And in fact, I think it's very difficult to see how they won't destroy us
وفي الواقع، أظنه من الصعب جداً أن نرى كيف أنها لن تدمرنا
or inspire us to destroy ourselves.
أو تلهمنا أن ندمر أنفسنا.
And yet if you're anything like me,
ومع ذلك إذا كنتم تشبهونني في شيء
you'll find that it's fun to think about these things.
فستجدون أنه من الممتع التفكير بهذه الأشياء.
And that response is part of the problem.
وتلك الإجابة هي جزء من المشكلة.
OK? That response should worry you.
حسناً؟ تلك الإجابة يجب أن تُقلقكم.
And if I were to convince you in this talk
وإذا كان عليَّ أن أقنعكم في هذه المحادثة
that we were likely to suffer a global famine,
أنه من المرجح أننا سوف نعاني من مجاعة عالمية
either because of climate change or some other catastrophe,
إما بسبب تغيُّر المناخ، أو بسبب كارثة أخرى،
and that your grandchildren, or their grandchildren,
وأن أحفادكم، أو أحفادهم،
are very likely to live like this,
من المرجح جداً أن يعيشوا، هكذا
you wouldn't think,
فلن يخطر ببالكم.
"Interesting.
"مثير للاهتمام".
I like this TED Talk."
تعجبني محادثة TED هذه.
Famine isn't fun.
المجاعة ليست مسلية.
Death by science fiction, on the other hand, is fun,
الموت عن طريق الخيال العلمي، من ناحية أخرى، مسلٍّ،
and one of the things that worries me most about the development of AI at this point
وأحد الأشياء التي تقلقني للغاية بسبب تطور الذكاء الاصطناعي عند هذه النقطة
is that we seem unable to marshal an appropriate emotional response
هي أننا نبدو وكأننا غير قادرين على إبداء استجابة عاطفية ملائمة
to the dangers that lie ahead.
للأخطار التي تنتظرنا.
I am unable to marshal this response, and I'm giving this talk.
أنا غير قادر على إبداء هذه الاستجابة، وأنا أقوم بهذه المحادثة.
It's as though we stand before two doors.
يبدو الأمر وكأننا نقف أمام بابين.
Behind door number one,
خلف الباب رقم واحد،
we stop making progress in building intelligent machines.
نتوقف عن تحقيق التقدُّم في بناء الآليات الذكية.
Our computer hardware and software just stops getting better for some reason.
معدات حاسوبنا وبرمجياته تتوقف عن التحسن لسببٍ ما وحسب.
Now take a moment to consider why this might happen.
خذوا الآن لحظة للتفكير لماذا قد يحدث ذلك.
I mean, given how valuable intelligence and automation are,
أعني، بافتراض مدى نفع الذكاء والأتمتة،
we will continue to improve our technology if we are at all able to.
فإننا سنستمر بتحسين التكنولوجيا الخاصة بنا إذا كان بإمكاننا أصلاً.
What could stop us from doing this?
ما الذي قد يمنعنا من فعل هذا؟
A full-scale nuclear war?
حربٌ نووية على جميع المقاييس؟
A global pandemic?
وباء عالمي؟
An asteroid impact?
اصطدام كويكب؟
Justin Bieber becoming president of the United States?
أن يصبح جاستن بيبر رئيساً للولايات المتحدة؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The point is, something would have to destroy civilization as we know it.
الخلاصة هي، شيءٌ ما عليه تدمير الحضارة كما نعرفها.
You have to imagine how bad it would have to be
عليكم تخيُّل كم عليه أن يكون سيئاً
to prevent us from making improvements in our technology
لكي يمنعنا من تحقيق تحسينات في التكنولوجيا الخاصة بنا
permanently,
بشكل دائم،
generation after generation.
جيلاً بعد جيل.
Almost by definition, this is the worst thing
تقريباً بالتعريف، هذا أسوأ شيء
that's ever happened in human history.
يمكن أن يحصل في تاريخ البشرية.
So the only alternative,
لذا البديل الوحيد،
and this is what lies behind door number two,
وهو الذي يوجد خلف الباب رقم اثنين،
is that we continue to improve our intelligent machines
هو أن نستمر بتحسين آلاتنا الذكية
year after year after year.
سنة بعد سنة بعد سنة.
At a certain point, we will build machines that are smarter than we are,
وعند نقطة معينة، سنبني آلياتٍ أذكى مما نحن عليه،
and once we have machines that are smarter than we are,
وحالما يصبح لدينا آليات أذكى مننا،
they will begin to improve themselves.
سوف تبدأ بتحسين نفسها.
And then we risk what the mathematician IJ Good called
وعندها سنواجه ما دعاه عالم الرياضيات IJ Good
an "intelligence explosion,"
"انفجاراً ذكائياً"
that the process could get away from us.
وأن العملية يمكن أن تفلت من بين أيدينا.
Now, this is often caricatured, as I have here,
الآن، هذا يتم عمله كرسم كاريكاتيري، كما أفعل هنا
as a fear that armies of malicious robots
كخوفٍ من جيوش ميليشيا من الرجال الآليين
will attack us.
التي ستهاجمنا.
But that isn't the most likely scenario.
ولكن هذا ليس السيناريو الأكثر احتمالاً.
It's not that our machines will become spontaneously malevolent.
الأمر ليس أن آلياتنا ستصبح حاقدة بشكل عفوي
The concern is really that we will build machines
المقلق حقاً هو أننا نبني آليات
that are so much more competent than we are
أكثر كفاءة مما نحن عليه
that the slightest divergence between their goals and our own
وأن أقل اختلاف بين أهدافها وأهدافنا
could destroy us.
يمكن أن يدمرنا.
Just think about how we relate to ants.
فقط فكروا بكيفية علاقتنا بالنمل
We don't hate them.
نحن لا نكرههم.
We don't go out of our way to harm them.
ولا نخرج عن طريقنا لنؤذيهم.
In fact, sometimes we take pains not to harm them.
في الواقع، أحياناً نتحمل آلاماً لكي لا نؤذيهم.
We step over them on the sidewalk.
نحن نمشي من فوقهم على الرصيف.
But whenever their presence
ولكن عندما يكون لوجودهم
seriously conflicts with one of our goals,
تعارض جدِّي مع أحد أهدافنا،
let's say when constructing a building like this one,
لنقل مثلاً عند إنشاء بناء كهذا،
we annihilate them without a qualm.
نقوم بإبادتهم بدون أي تأنيب ضمير.
The concern is that we will one day build machines
والقلق من أننا يوماً ما سوف نبني آليات
that, whether they're conscious or not,
والتي، سواءٌ كانت مدركة أم لا،
could treat us with similar disregard.
قد تعاملنا بمثل هذا الاستخفاف.
Now, I suspect this seems far-fetched to many of you.
والآن، أنا أشك أن هذا أبعد ما يكون عن العديد منكم.
I bet there are those of you who doubt that superintelligent AI is possible,
وأراهن على أن هنالك منكم من يشك أن الذكاء الاصطناعي الخارق الذكاء ممكن،
much less inevitable.
أو حتى محتوم.
But then you must find something wrong with one of the following assumptions.
ولكن مع ذلك يجب عليكم أن تجدوا شيئاً ما خاطئاً في أحد الافتراضات التالية.
And there are only three of them.
وهنالك ثلاثة منهم.
Intelligence is a matter of information processing in physical systems.
الذكاء هو مسألة معالجة للمعلومات في الأنظمة الفيزيائية.
Actually, this is a little bit more than an assumption.
في الواقع، هذا أكثر بقليل من مجرد افتراض.
We have already built narrow intelligence into our machines,
نحن قمنا مسبقاً ببناء ذكاء محدود في آلياتنا،
and many of these machines perform
والعديد من هذه الآليات تقوم بالأداء
at a level of superhuman intelligence already.
في مستوى الذكاء البشري الخارق أصلاً.
And we know that mere matter
ونعلم أن المادة المجردة
can give rise to what is called "general intelligence,"
بإمكانها أن تعطي زيادة لما يدعى "بالذكاء العام"،
an ability to think flexibly across multiple domains,
القدرة على التفكير بمرونة في عدة مجالات،
because our brains have managed it. Right?
لأن دماغنا قام بتدبر الأمر. صحيح؟
I mean, there's just atoms in here,
أنا أعني، هناك ذرات فقط هنا،
and as long as we continue to build systems of atoms
وطالما نستمر ببناء أنظمة من الذرات
that display more and more intelligent behavior,
والتي تُبدي سلوكاً متزايداً أكثر وأكثر من الذكاء
we will eventually, unless we are interrupted,
فإننا في النهاية، إلا إذا تمَّت مقاطعتنا،
we will eventually build general intelligence
في النهاية سوف نبني ذكاءً عاماً
into our machines.
في آلياتنا.
It's crucial to realize that the rate of progress doesn't matter,
من المصيري أن ندرك أن معدل التطور لا يهم،
because any progress is enough to get us into the end zone.
لأن أي تطور هو كافٍ لإيصالنا إلى منطقة النهاية.
We don't need Moore's law to continue. We don't need exponential progress.
لا نحتاج قانون Moore للاستمرار. لا نحتاج التطور الأسي.
We just need to keep going.
نحتاج فقط لأن نستمر بالمضي قدماً
The second assumption is that we will keep going.
الافتراض الثاني هو أننا سنستمر بالمضي قدماً.
We will continue to improve our intelligent machines.
سنستمر بتحسين آلياتنا الذكية.
And given the value of intelligence --
وبافتراض أهمية الذكاء --
I mean, intelligence is either the source of everything we value
أنا أعني، أن الذكاء هو إما مصدر لكل شيءٍ نقدِّره
or we need it to safeguard everything we value.
أو أننا نحتاجه لحماية كل شيءٍ نقدُّره.
It is our most valuable resource.
إنه المنبع الأكثر أهمية لدينا.
So we want to do this.
لذلك نحتاج لفعل التالي.
We have problems that we desperately need to solve.
لدينا مشاكل نحن بحاجة ماسِّة لحلها.
We want to cure diseases like Alzheimer's and cancer.
نريد شفاء الأمراض كالزهايمر والسرطان.
We want to understand economic systems. We want to improve our climate science.
نريد أن نفهم الأنظمة الاقتصادية. نريد تحسين علم المناخ الخاص بنا.
So we will do this, if we can.
لذلك سنفعل ذلك، إذا استطعنا.
The train is already out of the station, and there's no brake to pull.
القطار غادر المحطة بالفعل، ولا يوجد مكابح لشدها.
Finally, we don't stand on a peak of intelligence,
وأخيراً، نحن لا نقف عند قمة الذكاء،
or anywhere near it, likely.
أو في أي مكان قريب منها، على ما يبدو،
And this really is the crucial insight.
وهذا حقاً هو البصيرة المصيرية.
This is what makes our situation so precarious,
هذا ما يجعل موقفنا متزعزعاً للغاية،
and this is what makes our intuitions about risk so unreliable.
وهذا ما يجعل حدسنا بما يخص الخطورة لا يُعتمد عليه أبداً.
Now, just consider the smartest person who has ever lived.
والآن، فكروا فقط بأذكى شخص عاش في أي وقتٍ مضى.
On almost everyone's shortlist here is John von Neumann.
تقريباً على قائمة الجميع القصيرة يوجد John von Neumann.
I mean, the impression that von Neumann made on the people around him,
أعني، الانطباع الذي تركه von Neumann على الناس المحيطين به،
and this included the greatest mathematicians and physicists of his time,
وهذا يشمل أعظم علماء الرياضيات والفيزياء في عصره،
is fairly well-documented.
بالكاد تم توثيقه بشكل جيد.
If only half the stories about him are half true,
إذا كانت نصف القصص فقط عنه نصف صحيحة،
there's no question
فلا يوجد شك
he's one of the smartest people who has ever lived.
أنه أحد أذكى الأشخاص الذين عاشوا في أي وقتٍ مضى.
So consider the spectrum of intelligence.
لذلك باعتبار طيف الذكاء.
Here we have John von Neumann.
هنا لدينا John von Neumann.
And then we have you and me.
وهنا لدينا أنتم وأنا.
And then we have a chicken.
وثم هنا لدينا دجاجة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Sorry, a chicken.
آسف، دجاجة.
There's no reason for me to make this talk more depressing than it needs to be.
لا يوجد سبب يجعلني أجعل هذه المحادثة أكثر إحباطاً مما يحتاجه الأمر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It seems overwhelmingly likely, however, that the spectrum of intelligence
يبدو أنه ساحق على الأرجح، ومع ذلك، يمتد طيف الذكاء
extends much further than we currently conceive,
أبعد بكثير مما نتصور حالياً،
and if we build machines that are more intelligent than we are,
وإذا قمنا ببناء آلات أذكى مما نحن عليه،
they will very likely explore this spectrum
فهي على الأرجح ستستكشف الطيف
in ways that we can't imagine,
بطرقٍ لا نستطيع تخيلها،
and exceed us in ways that we can't imagine.
وسف تتعدانا بطرقٍ لا يمكننا تخيلها.
And it's important to recognize that this is true by virtue of speed alone.
ومن المهم أن ندرك أن هذا صحيح بخصوص تأثير السرعة وحدها.
Right? So imagine if we just built a superintelligent AI
صحيح؟ إذاً تخيلوا إذا بنينا ذكاءً صنعياً خارق الذكاء
that was no smarter than your average team of researchers
ولم يكن أذكى من فريق الباحثين العادي الخاص بكم
at Stanford or MIT.
في ستانفورد أو معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا.
Well, electronic circuits function about a million times faster
حسناً، الدارات الالكترونية تعمل بشكل أسرع بحوالي ملايين المرات
than biochemical ones,
من تلك الكيميائية الحيوية،
so this machine should think about a million times faster
لذا هذه الآلة يجب أن تفكر أسرع بملايين المرات
than the minds that built it.
من العقول التي قامت ببنائها.
So you set it running for a week,
لذا إذا تركتها تعمل لمدة أسبوع،
and it will perform 20,000 years of human-level intellectual work,
فسوف تؤدي ما يعادل 20,000 سنة من العمل بمستوى الذكاء البشري،
week after week after week.
أسبوع بعد أسبوع بعد أسبوع.
How could we even understand, much less constrain,
كيف بإمكاننا حتى أن نفهم، أو حتى أن نُقيّد،
a mind making this sort of progress?
عقلاً يصنع هذا النوع من التطور؟
The other thing that's worrying, frankly,
والأمر الآخر المقلق، بصراحة،
is that, imagine the best case scenario.
هو أن، تخيل أفضل سيناريو.
So imagine we hit upon a design of superintelligent AI
إذاً تخيلوا أننا اكتشفنا تصميماً للذكاء الصنعي فائق الذكاء
that has no safety concerns.
وليس لديه مخاوف سلامة.
We have the perfect design the first time around.
لدينا التصميم المثالي للمرة الأولى.
It's as though we've been handed an oracle
وكأنه تم تسليمنا نبوءة
that behaves exactly as intended.
تتصرَّف تماماً كما ينبغي عليها.
Well, this machine would be the perfect labor-saving device.
هذه الآلة ستكون المثلى لتوفير العمالة.
It can design the machine that can build the machine
بإمكانها تصميم آلية ستقوم ببناء الآلة
that can do any physical work,
التي بإمكانها القيام بأي عمل فيزيائي،
powered by sunlight,
تعمل بضوء الشمس،
more or less for the cost of raw materials.
ومهما يكن من أجل كلفة المواد الخام.
So we're talking about the end of human drudgery.
إذاً نحن نتكلم عن نهاية الكدح البشري.
We're also talking about the end of most intellectual work.
نحن أيضا نتكلم عن نهاية العمل الذكائي.
So what would apes like ourselves do in this circumstance?
فماذا قد تفعل القرود أمثالنا في هذا الظرف؟
Well, we'd be free to play Frisbee and give each other massages.
حسناً، سنكون متفرغين للعب بالصحن الطائر وتبادل الرسائل مع بعضنا.
Add some LSD and some questionable wardrobe choices,
أضف بعض الـLSD مع اختيارات اللباس المشكوك بأمرها،
and the whole world could be like Burning Man.
وبإمكان العالم كله أن يصبح كفيلم Burning Man.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, that might sound pretty good,
حسناً، هذا قد يبدو جيداً جداً،
but ask yourself what would happen
ولكن اسألوا أنفسكم ماذا قد يسبب هذا
under our current economic and political order?
لاقتصادنا الحالي ووضعنا السياسي؟
It seems likely that we would witness
يبدو أننا سنشهد على الأرجح
a level of wealth inequality and unemployment
مستوى من تفاوت الثروات والبطالة
that we have never seen before.
الذي لم نشهده أبداً من قبل
Absent a willingness to immediately put this new wealth
غياب الرغبة لوضع هذه الثروة الجديدة فوراً
to the service of all humanity,
في خدمة جميع البشرية،
a few trillionaires could grace the covers of our business magazines
بعض أصحاب التريليونات سوف يُشرِّفون أغلفة مجلات أعمالنا
while the rest of the world would be free to starve.
بينما يكون باقي العالم متفرغاً لكي يتضور جوعاً.
And what would the Russians or the Chinese do
وماذا سيفعل الروس أو الصينيون
if they heard that some company in Silicon Valley
إذا سمعوا أن شركةً ما في Silicon Valley
was about to deploy a superintelligent AI?
كانت على وشك نشر الذكاء الا فائق الذكاء؟
This machine would be capable of waging war,
هذه الآلة ستكون قادرة على شن حرب،
whether terrestrial or cyber,
سواء كانت على الأرض أو على الإنترنت،
with unprecedented power.
بقوة غير مسبوقة.
This is a winner-take-all scenario.
هذا السيناريو هو الذي يربح كل شيء
To be six months ahead of the competition here
أن تكون متقدماً بستة أشهر على المنافسة في هذه الحالة
is to be 500,000 years ahead,
تعني أن تكون متقدماً بـ500,000 سنة،
at a minimum.
بأقل حد.
So it seems that even mere rumors of this kind of breakthrough
وبالتالي يبدو أنه حتى الإشاعات المحضة بما يخص النوع من الاكتشافات
could cause our species to go berserk.
يمكن أن تجعل فصائلنا تهتاج.
Now, one of the most frightening things,
والآن، أكثر الأشياء إخافة،
in my view, at this moment,
من وجهة نظري، في هذه اللحظة،
are the kinds of things that AI researchers say
هي النوع من الأشياء التي يقولها باحثو الذكاء الاصطناعي عندما
when they want to be reassuring.
يريدون أن يكونوا مُطمئِنين.
And the most common reason we're told not to worry is time.
والسبب الأكثر شيوعاً الذي يُقال لنا ألا نقلق بسببه هو الوقت
This is all a long way off, don't you know.
هذا كله سيمر، ألا تعلم.
This is probably 50 or 100 years away.
هذا من المحتمل بعد 50 أو 100 سنة.
One researcher has said,
قال أحد الباحثين،
"Worrying about AI safety
"القلق بشأن سلامة الذكاء الاصطناعي
is like worrying about overpopulation on Mars."
هو كالقلق بشأن زيادة التعداد السكاني على المريخ"
This is the Silicon Valley version
هذه نسخة Silicon Valley
of "don't worry your pretty little head about it."
من "لا تُقلق رأسك الجميل الصغير بهذا".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
No one seems to notice
لا يبدو أن أحداً يلاحظ
that referencing the time horizon
أن الإشارة للحد الزمني
is a total non sequitur.
ليس له عواقب بتاتاً.
If intelligence is just a matter of information processing,
إذا كان الذكاء هو مجرد مسألة معالجة معلومات،
and we continue to improve our machines,
ونحن نستمر بتحسين آلياتنا،
we will produce some form of superintelligence.
فسنقوم بإنتاج شكلٍ ما من الذكاء الفائق.
And we have no idea how long it will take us
وليس لدينا فكرة كم سيستغرق هذا مننا
to create the conditions to do that safely.
لخلق الشروط للقيام بذلك بأمان.
Let me say that again.
دعوني أقل ذلك مرة أخرى.
We have no idea how long it will take us
ليس لدينا فكرة كم سيستغرق الأمر مننا
to create the conditions to do that safely.
لخلق الشروط للقيام بذلك بأمان.
And if you haven't noticed, 50 years is not what it used to be.
وإذا لم تلاحظوا، لم تعد الخمسون سنة كما كانت عليه.
This is 50 years in months.
هذه 50 سنة في أشهر.
This is how long we've had the iPhone.
هذه المدة التي امتلكنا فيها الـiPhone
This is how long "The Simpsons" has been on television.
هذه المدة التي انعرض فيها The Simpsons على التلفاز
Fifty years is not that much time
خمسون سنة هي ليست بالوقت الكثير
to meet one of the greatest challenges our species will ever face.
لمواجهة أحد أكبر التحديات الذي سيواجه لفصيلتنا.
Once again, we seem to be failing to have an appropriate emotional response
مرة أخرى، يبدو أننا نفشل في امتلاك الاستجابة العاطفية الملائمة
to what we have every reason to believe is coming.
لما يوجد لدينا أكثر من سبب للإيمكان بأنه قادم
The computer scientist Stuart Russell has a nice analogy here.
عالم الحاسوب Stuart Russell لديه تحليل لطيف هنا.
He said, imagine that we received a message from an alien civilization,
هو يقول، تخيلوا أننا استلمنا رسالة من حضارة الفضائيين،
which read:
والتي كانت:
"People of Earth,
"سكان الأرض،
we will arrive on your planet in 50 years.
سوف نصل إلى كوكبكم خلال 50 سنة.
Get ready."
استعدوا."
And now we're just counting down the months until the mothership lands?
والآن نقوم بالعد التنازلي للأشهر حتى تهبط السفينة الأم؟
We would feel a little more urgency than we do.
سنشعر بالعجلة أكثر مما نفعل الآن بقليل.
Another reason we're told not to worry
يُقال لنا ألا نقلق لسببٍ آخر
is that these machines can't help but share our values
هو أن هذه الآليات ليس بوسعها إلا مشاركتنا منافعها
because they will be literally extensions of ourselves.
لأنها ستكون حرفياً امتداداً لأنفسنا.
They'll be grafted onto our brains,
ستكون مُطعَّمة مع أدمغتنا،
and we'll essentially become their limbic systems.
ونحن سنصبح جوهرياً أنظمتها الحوفية.
Now take a moment to consider
الآن خذوا لحظة للتفكير
that the safest and only prudent path forward,
أن الطريق الوحيد الآمن والحكيم للأمام،
recommended,
الذي يُنصح به،
is to implant this technology directly into our brains.
هو زرع هذه التكنولوجيا مباشرةً في أدمغتنا.
Now, this may in fact be the safest and only prudent path forward,
قد يكون الطريق الوحيد الآمن والحكيم للأمام،
but usually one's safety concerns about a technology
ولكن عادةً يكون للمرء مخاوف عن كون التكنولوجيا
have to be pretty much worked out before you stick it inside your head.
مفهومة لحدٍّ ما قبل أن تدخلها داخل رأسك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The deeper problem is that building superintelligent AI on its own
المشكلة الأعمق أن بناء ذكاء اصطناعي فائق الذكاء بمفرده
seems likely to be easier
يبدو على الأرجح أنه أسهل
than building superintelligent AI
من بناء ذكاء اصطناعي فائق الذكاء
and having the completed neuroscience
وامتلاك علم الأعصاب الكامل
that allows us to seamlessly integrate our minds with it.
الذي يسمح لنا بمكاملة عقولنا معه بسلاسة.
And given that the companies and governments doing this work
وبافتراض أن الشركات والحكومات التي تقوم بهذا العمل
are likely to perceive themselves as being in a race against all others,
على الأرجح ستعي كونها في سباق ضد الآخرين جميعاً،
given that to win this race is to win the world,
وبافتراض أن الفوز في هذا السباق هو الفوز بالعالم،
provided you don't destroy it in the next moment,
بفرض أنك لن تدمره في الشهر التالي،
then it seems likely that whatever is easier to do
فبالتالي يبدو على الأرجح أنه مهما يكن الأسهل فعله
will get done first.
سيتم الانتهاء منه أولاً.
Now, unfortunately, I don't have a solution to this problem,
الآن، لسوء الحظ، لا أمتلك حلاً لهذه المشكلة،
apart from recommending that more of us think about it.
بمعزل عن توصية أن يفكِّر المزيد مننا به.
I think we need something like a Manhattan Project
أظن أننا بحاجة شيء ما مثل "مشروع مانهاتن"
on the topic of artificial intelligence.
لموضوع الذكاء الاصطناعي.
Not to build it, because I think we'll inevitably do that,
ليس لبنائه، لأنني أظننا سنفعل ذلك حتماً،
but to understand how to avoid an arms race
ولكن لفهم كيفية تجنب سباق الأذرع
and to build it in a way that is aligned with our interests.
ولبنائه بطريقة منحازة مع اهتماماتنا.
When you're talking about superintelligent AI
عندما تتحدث عن ذكاء اصطناعي فائق الذكاء
that can make changes to itself,
يمكنه إحداث تغيير لنفسه،
it seems that we only have one chance to get the initial conditions right,
يبدو أن لدينا فرصة واحدة للقيام بالشروط الابتدائية بشكل صحيح،
and even then we will need to absorb
وحتى حينها سنكون بحاجة امتصاص
the economic and political consequences of getting them right.
العواقب الاقتصادية والسياسية من القيام بها بشكل صحيح.
But the moment we admit
ولكن في اللحظة التي نعترف فيها
that information processing is the source of intelligence,
أن معالجة المعلومات هي مصدر الذكاء،
that some appropriate computational system is what the basis of intelligence is,
وأن بعض أنظمة الحاسوب الملائمة تُعبِّر عن أساس الذكاء،
and we admit that we will improve these systems continuously,
ونعترف أننا سوف نحسِّن هذه الأنظمة باستمرار،
and we admit that the horizon of cognition very likely far exceeds
ونعترف أن أفق الإدراك على الأرجح يتجاوز
what we currently know,
الذي نعرفه حالياً بكثير،
then we have to admit
وبالتالي علينا الاعتراف
that we are in the process of building some sort of god.
أننا في مرحلة بناء نوع ما من الآلهة.
Now would be a good time
الآن سيكون وقتاً جيداً
to make sure it's a god we can live with.
للتأكد من أنه إله نستطيع العيش معه.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)